What did I want to be?
我想成為什麼樣的人？
Yes. What did you want to be when you grew up?
對，你小時候想成為什麼樣的人？
A man with strong bonds of friendship, of course.
當然是擁抱炙熱友誼的男人啊
What does that mean?
什麼意思？
I think he means
我想他的意思是…
a guy who cares about his friends.
成為一個關心朋友的男人吧
That's right.
沒錯
But that's normal, right?
但那不是很普通嗎？
No, it's not!
一點都不普通
For example, one day, out of the blue,
舉例來說，突然有一天
your friend comes to your place carrying a suitcase.
你的朋友帶著行李箱來到你家
And inside the suitcase is
而行李箱裡裝的是…
a dismembered body!
被肢解的屍體
Oh, no!
不
For some reason, that friend ended up killing someone.
那個朋友，不知為何殺了人
Then?
然後呢？
That friend came to me because he knew he could depend on me.
那個朋友來找我 是因為他知道信得過我
-But you know, that's murder, right? -Right!
-但你知道那是謀殺吧？ -對啊
I know!
我知道啦
I know that, but I'll listen to his whole story.
我知道，但我會聽他解釋
That's true friendship.
這就是真正的友情
That's the strong bond of male friendship!
男人間炙熱的友誼
Ouch! That's hot!
好痛，好燙
Wouldn't you tell the police?
但你不會告訴警察嗎？
You can do that later.
可以晚點再說啊
Later?
晚點？
Most importantly,
最重要的是
you listen to your friend's whole story.
聽你朋友訴說完整的故事
That's what's key.
那才是重點
Oh, man!
真是的
Kids do the work.
那是小孩該做的事
Why can't you answer sometimes, Dad?
爸，為什麼你都不去應門？
-Hurry up and answer it. -Be a good boy and work.
-動作快啊 -當個乖孩子，快去
Whoa!
哇！
Shuji's friend has a suitcase!
哥的朋友帶了行李箱
-A suitcase? -Yes.
-行李箱？ -對
There's big trouble.
這下麻煩大了
This is really bad.
真的糟了
What kind of trouble?
什麼樣的麻煩？
-Will you listen to my story? -Yes.
-你願意聽我說嗎？ -願意
I'll listen, but...
我會聽，但是…
what's inside that?
那裡面有什麼？
Want to see?
想看嗎？
What's that?
那是什麼？
My overnight stuff!
我的過夜行李
Wait! You want to stay here?
等等，你想住在這裡？
I've run away.
我離家出走了
You've run away?
離家出走？
-Yes. -"Yes"? Is that any way to talk?
-正解 -“正解”？哪有人這樣說話的？
Hey!
喂
You're supposed to tuck your pajamas inside your pants.
睡衣就該塞進褲子裡
In! Put them in!
塞進去，快點
-You too, pops. -"Pops"?
-你也是，老爹 -“老爹”？
What? Why tuck them in?
什麼？為什麼要塞進去？
It keeps your tummy warm.
可以讓肚子保暖
That's one of the fundamentals of life!
這可是生活的基本常識啊
-Tuck yours in too, Shuji! -Leave me be!
-修二，你也快塞進去吧 -別管我
Tuck in, Shuji!
修二，快塞進去吧
What's that?
那是什麼？
I thought this would be helpful when turning out the light.
我想這樣關燈時，應該會很方便
Did you make this pig?
這隻豬是你做的嗎？
Nobuta did.
是野豬做的
Don't you know about Nobuta power?
你不知道野豬能量嗎？
What's that?
那是什麼？
-Excuse me. -What? What are you doing?
-打擾了 -什麼？你在做什麼？
You're creeping me out!
好噁心
Don't copy me, man.
別學我
"Don't copy me, man."
“別學我”
What a pain.
真煩人
It sure is warm.
好溫暖喔
Why the heck did you run away?
你到底為什麼要離家出走？
Well, my old man came to my boarding house.
我老爹跑來我寄宿的家
What? You mean your dad?
什麼？你是說你爸嗎？
Yes. My real dad.
對，我的生父
He told me to start working for his company. We got in a big fight.
他叫我去他們公司工作 我們大吵一架
I see.
這樣啊
Your dad's the president of that company, isn't he?
你爸是那家公司的社長，對吧？
That's right.
沒錯
But I don't want to go back home.
但我不想回家
I like Mr. Hirayama and I can drink soymilk too.
我喜歡大叔，還可以喝豆子乳
You…
跟你…
and Nobuta, every day…
還有野豬，每天…
"Every day"?
“每天”？
"Every day" what?
每天怎樣？
Good night.
晚安
So how long are you going to stay at our place?
你要在我們家住到什麼時候？
What's wrong with it? It's lots of fun, don't you think?
怎麼了？很好玩啊，你不覺得嗎？
Watch out! Oops!
小心
What's wrong?
怎麼了？
I was wondering
我在想…
if we'll end up like these incredibly boring-looking dudes.
我們會不會變得 跟這些看起來超無趣的傢伙一樣
I don't want to be like that.
我不想變那樣
Not like that! I don't want to be like that!
不要，不要變那樣，我不想變成那樣
I'll hand out the post-graduation surveys now.
我現在要發畢業志向調查表
Make sure you hand them back in by next week.
下週前務必交回
Decide my future by next week?
下週前就要決定我的未來？
One week isn't enough to decide on the rest of my life.
一週的時間 要我怎麼決定往後的人生？
Shuji. What are you going to do?
修二，你打算做什麼？
-Me? -Yes.
-我？ -對啊
-I haven't decided anything. -Really?
-我完全還沒決定 -真的嗎？
Tani will try for a sports scholarship in tennis.
阿谷會爭取網球運動獎學金
-Really? -Nami's going to fashion school.
-奈美要去念設計學校
Misaki wants to go to any college with an English department.
美咲說想去任何有英文科系的大學
-That's pretty amazing. -Yes.
-真了不起 -對啊
Whoa. It's like everyone else has seriously thought this stuff over.
大家好像都很認真思考過這件事了
POST-GRADUATION SURVEY
（畢業志向調查表）
What will you do? You going to work at your dad's company?
你要做什麼？去你爸的公司上班嗎？
I'm sick of talking about what to do after graduation.
我受夠討論畢業後要做什麼了
Don't you think there's something more important we need to do?
不覺得我們有更重要的事要做嗎？
What's that?
是什麼？
Ouch.
好痛
Aren't we going to make Nobuta popular?
我們不是要讓野豬變得有人氣嗎？
That poses lots of problems too.
這件事也有很多問題
No matter what we do, it always starts crazy rumors.
不管我們做什麼都會引起奇怪的謠言
Who the heck keeps making trouble for us?
到底是哪個傢伙一直找我們麻煩？
Must be someone with nothing else better to do.
一定是沒有別的事可做的人
Why don't we spread rumors this time?
這次換我們散播謠言怎麼樣？
Good idea! We'll get the jump on them.
好主意，我們先發制人
I've had it with letting them always get the better of us.
我已經受夠總是任由他們欺負
I've had it!
受夠了
Okay!
好
-On go, okay? -Yes.
-數到二發射？ -好
Here goes.
開始囉
Ready. Nobuta!
一…野豬
Sorry.
抱歉
Ready. Go!
一、二
That's right. We can't keep doing silly stuff forever.
沒錯，我們沒辦法永遠做些傻事
We won't be able to
我們能在這裡…
gaze out into the sky from here
眺望天空的時間
for too much longer.
已經所剩無幾了
Ciao!
再見
-Shuji! -Yes?
-修二 -什麼？
I've been wondering, what's that on your bag?
我一直在想 你包包上那個是什麼東西？
There isn't anything on my bag.
我包包上什麼都沒有啊
This isn't anything.
這沒什麼
That's totally cute!
超可愛的
-Yes! It sure is! -This?
-對啊 -這個嗎？
-You think it's cute? -Did you make that yourself?
-可愛嗎？ -這是你自己做的嗎？
-You're really good at that. -Yes! It's so cute!
-你真的很厲害 -對啊，好可愛
Actually, this was made by Kotani.
其實這是小谷做的
-No way! Kotani made it? -Yes, Kotani did.
-不會吧？是小谷做的？ -對，小谷做的
Kotani made that!
是小谷做的
-Go on now! -Cut that out!
-快點啦 -別鬧了
-Kotani! Kotani! -Wait!
-小谷… -等等…
Will you make me one too?
妳也可以幫我做一個嗎？
-Me too! -Yes! Me too!
-我也要 -我也要一個
Okay.
好
All right!
-太好了
Can you make a girl one?
妳可以做女生版的嗎？
Oh, that'll be cute for sure!
一定很可愛
You know what?
不如這樣吧
To get more people to know about Nobuta, let's sell Nobuta merch.
為了讓更多人認識野豬 我們來賣野豬的商品吧
It'll be called…
就叫它…
the Nobuta Keychain.
野豬鑰匙圈
-What do you think? -Will that sell?
-如何？ -賣得出去嗎？
Nowadays, even with something as wacky as this, they say,
現在就算是這種古怪的東西 大家也會嚷嚷
"How cute! How totally cute!" And "How kooky cute!"
“真可愛，太可愛了” 或是“又怪又可愛”
And "100% cute!" It'll be a hit for sure.
還有“超級無敵可愛” 一定會大賣的
And "Piggy cute!" That's exactly what it is! How dumb!
還有“豬豬可愛” 那本來就是豬啊，真蠢
It'll be the talk of the school.
這會成為學校的話題
If we can show people this unexpected side of Nobuta,
如果我們能讓大家看到 野豬令人意想不到的一面
your popularity will soar for sure.
野豬的人氣一定會飆升
Then
那麼…
let's hand them out for free.
我們就免費發放吧
No, don't you see?
不，妳不懂嗎？
People only appreciate something when they pay for it.
人們只有付了錢才會懂得欣賞
I see.
原來是這樣
So what we'll do is, we'll get Nobuta's popularity to skyrocket fast.
所以，我們要做的是 讓野豬的人氣迅速飆升
-At last, we're going to the majors! -You bet.
-我們終於要來真的了啊 -當然
So I'm counting on you to pay for making the merch.
所以商品的製作費用就要由你負責了
I'm fighting with my dad, so I don't have any money.
我和老爹吵架，口袋空空沒有錢
Seriously?
真的假的？
HIRAYAMA TOFU SHOP
（平山豆腐店）
Yo!
來啦
Good evening.
晚安
Say, Mr. Hirayama, is my dad still here?
大叔，我爸還在嗎？
It's a little late for that.
現在問這個有點太遲了吧
He left last night.
他昨晚離開了
Really?
真的嗎？
Thank goodness.
太好了
Okay, let's go.
好，走吧
Come right in.
請進
Ouch!
好痛
What happened?
怎麼回事？
Is this the aftermath of your fight?
這就是你們吵架後的現場嗎？
One thing my dad has got are strong arms.
我爸的手臂可強壯了
He's like that.
他就是這樣
There! Done!
好了，完成
Is this too chintzy?
會看起來太廉價嗎？
No. In fact, it's that chintzy look that makes it cute.
不，就是那種廉價感才可愛
-It's cute? -Yes.
-可愛嗎？ -對啊
Nobuta power charge!
野豬能量，注入
What?
什麼？
Since we're making these, I want to make sure they sell.
既然要做，我希望能賣得出去
Give me that one you filled with Nobuta power.
把注入野豬能量的那個給我吧
Why?
什麼意思？
-Didn't you know? -What?
-你不知道嗎？ -什麼？
The potency of Nobuta power is absolutely phenomenal!
野豬能量的威力可是很強大的
-Nobuta power potency? -Yes.
-野豬能量的威力？ -對啊
That's what we can do!
就是這個
What's that?
這個是什麼？
What we'll do is,
我們要做的是…
we'll spread the rumor that this thing grants wishes.
散播這東西能實現願望的謠言
Girls love that kind of thing.
女孩子最喜歡這種事了
-Charms and stuff. -Rumors.
-護身符之類的 -都是謠言
-Rumors create more rumors. -Right!
-以訛傳訛的謠言 -沒錯
Then these could sell like crazy!
這玩意應該會大賣吧
-What do you think? -Are we going to be millionaires?
-你們覺得呢？ -我們會成為百萬富翁嗎？
We'll be rolling in cash!
我們會賺大錢的
Seriously? Awesome!
真的嗎？太棒了
-Morning. -Good morning.
-早安
Morning.
早安
What?
什麼？
What are you wishing for, Chie?
知惠，妳許了什麼願？
That I can talk with Bunta.
希望我能跟文太聊天
-You're so admirable!
-真羨慕
Bunta? Okay.
文太？好的
Bunta.
文太
Don't you think Chie is cute?
你不覺得知惠很可愛嗎？
Are you serious, man?
你是認真的嗎？
Serious, man.
我是認真的啊
See?
你看
Chie's pretty cute, right?
知惠很可愛吧？
Bunta is gradually starting to realize that Chie is cute.
文太開始覺得知惠很可愛了
Bunta can no longer escape the allure of Chie's charms.
現在文太無法逃脫知惠的魅力
She really is cute.
她真的好可愛
Hey!
喂
-She's cute! -You bet.
-好可愛 -當然
-I'm not sure why, but she's really cute!
-不知道為什麼，但她真的好可愛 -當然啦
What's more, I've heard that this thing will make your wishes come true.
而且聽說這個可以讓你實現願望
I'll give you one for free, Bunta. Okay?
文太，我就送你一個吧，好嗎？
A real man goes on the attack!
男子漢就要主動出擊啊
-Okay, Bunta? -Right.
-對吧，文太？ -對
You're cute, Chie.
知惠，妳好可愛
You're cute too, Bunta.
文太也很可愛啊
Yes!
太好了
Please. May more insects come to me.
拜託了，希望能讓我成為
Make me a great man!
吸引到更多昆蟲的好男人吧
Got it.
收到
Right there!
在那裡
"Right there!"
根本就沒有
Find anything?
有找到什麼嗎？
That's too close, I can't see anything, darn it!
太近了，根本看不到啊，可惡
-Look, would you?
-認真找啊
Great!
太棒了
-How about a Nobuta Power Charge Doll? -This is it!
-要不要來個注入野豬能量的娃娃？ -就是這個
-They're super cute! -This is the thing!
-超可愛的
-Hey, ladies? How about one? -No way!
-女士們，要不要來一個呢？ -不要
-Who wants that junk! -You actually want one, don't you?
-誰要那種垃圾 -妳其實很想要吧？
No pushing! No shoving! No running!
不要推，不要擠，請勿奔跑
That's great!
太好吃了
What's this? Pork?
這是什麼？豬肉？
Pork rib stew.
燉豬肋排
Pork rib stew? I've never had this before. Just kidding.
燉豬肋排？我還是第一次吃到 開玩笑的
It's really delicious.
真的很好吃
Lately, you hang around Kotani and Kusano, don't you?
你最近常跟小谷和草野在一起吧？
-I do? -Yes.
-有嗎？ -有啊
You think?
是嗎？
-I see you together a lot. -You do?
-我很常看到你們在一起 -是嗎？
It's because we're making these.
因為是我們在做這個
You're making that?
這是你做的嗎？
What?
什麼？
No, not really.
不，也不算是
I'm just helping a little.
我只是幫個忙
I give them ideas and stuff.
幫他們出主意
Like a part-time job.
就像打工一樣
-Is that right? -Yes. Part-time.
-這樣啊？ -對，打工
-You making money? -Yes. We're making money.
-有賺錢嗎？ -有啊，我們有賺錢了
-I'll treat you sometime. -Really?
-下次我請妳吃飯 -真的嗎？
-Yes. -All right!
-真的 -太好了
They're 200 yen each, right?
一個200日圓嗎？
That's 600 yen. Pay her.
這樣是600日圓，把錢給她
-Thank you. This is so nice. -May I get into Tokyo University.
-謝謝，真開心 -希望我能考上東大
Come on. Let's go.
我們走吧
-Thank you, Kotani. -Thank you.
-謝謝妳，小谷 -謝謝
Yes, Yes. Come on. Get going.
好了，我們走吧
They're really popular. I'll take one too.
真的很受歡迎呢，我也要一個
Thank you.
謝謝
This color is different than the others.
這個顏色跟其他的不一樣
That one… I made it for you.
這是…我為妳做的
Really?
真的嗎？
Thank you!
謝謝
You don't have to pay for it.
妳不用付錢
What? No, I'll pay.
什麼？不，我會付錢的
No.
不用了
You…
妳…
You're my f…
妳是我的朋…
You mean, you'll give me a discount because we're friends?
妳是說因為我們是朋友 所以要送我嗎？
Okay. Since we're friends, I'll have it for free.
好吧，既然是朋友，那我就收下了
Okay?
可以嗎？
Thank you. I'll take good care of it.
謝謝妳，我會好好保管的
Okay. I'll give you this for it.
那我用這個跟妳交換
A present.
禮物
Thank you.
謝謝
What's wrong?
怎麼了？
I…
我…
I made…
我交到…
I made a friend.
我交到朋友了
Amigo?
朋友？
Thank you.
謝謝
You know what?
妳知道嗎？
I like the head of taiyaki best.
我最喜歡鯛魚燒的頭了
When I eat the head,
我吃魚頭的時候
I feel happy.
就會覺得很幸福
I'm not sure why though.
雖然不知道為什麼
Did your friend give you this?
這是妳朋友送妳的嗎？
I see. So you made a friend.
這樣啊，妳交到朋友了
And Nobuta Power is selling well.
野豬能量商品也賣得很好
It's like everyone else wants a part of you now.
感覺好像大家都想搶走妳
It makes me sad.
好寂寞啊
I…
我…
I don't think I've changed at all.
覺得自己一點都沒變
Kotani!
小谷
There you are.
妳在這裡啊
Some girls are here asking for keychains.
有幾個女生想要買鑰匙圈
-Okay. -Let's go.
-好 -走吧
Who cares about that.
別管她們了
But some girls want them.
但有些女生想要鑰匙圈啊
Okay.
好吧
I guess producing means making something that everyone wants a part of.
難道改造 就是要讓大家都想搶走她嗎？
But that doesn't help me.
但這對我來說一點幫助也沒有
Right?
對吧？
-Yo!
-你來啦 -你好
-Is Akira here? -He'll be home soon.
-彰在嗎？ -他很快就回來了
-Come on in. -Thanks.
-請進 -謝謝
Sorry about the other day.
那天的事很抱歉
No problem.
沒事的
As usual, father-son arguments are brutal in your family.
你們父子吵架還是吵得那麼兇啊
So…
話說回來…
What is this?
這是什麼？
Akira's selling these at school, 200 yen each.
彰在學校賣這個，一個賣200日圓
What? Two hundred yen for this?
什麼？這個要200日圓？
That's better than my business.
比我的生意還好賺
The same price as tofu, but these are selling like hotcakes.
跟豆腐相同價錢 但是這些玩意賣得很好
Unbelievable, isn't it?
真是難以置信，對吧？
Ouch!
好痛
Damn it!
可惡
Lately,
最近…
even I can tell that I'm short-tempered.
連我都知道自己脾氣不太好
Maybe you're not getting enough carpaccio… I mean, calcium.
你是不是沒吃飯…我是說缺乏鈣質
I've had to lay off some people that I've worked with forever.
我不得不裁掉一些 跟我共事很久的老員工
I've gotten sick of my job.
我已經厭倦我的工作了
But you want your son to follow in your footsteps into it.
但你卻希望兒子步上你的後塵
It can't be helped.
沒辦法啊
Companies, you know,
有很多公司
they get into trouble over who it passes down to and some go under.
因為沒找對繼承人而惹上麻煩 甚至有些還倒閉了
They say the sooner you let everyone know who'll take over, the better.
越早讓大家知道接班人是誰越好
I'm home!
我回來了
Welcome home.
回來啦
What're you doing here, Dad? You're back?
爸，你怎麼又來了？
You're annoying me.
煩死人了
How can you call me annoying?
居然說我煩？
I'm here because you won't give me an answer!
還不都是因為你不給我答覆 我才會來
I told you, I'm not working there!
我說過了，我不要繼承公司
How dare you say that, you punk?
你在說什麼，臭小子？
I took over my dad's company and grew it!
我繼承我爸的公司，並且壯大它
Now it's your turn to make it even bigger!
現在輪到你讓公司變得更茁壯
You can't tell me what to do!
你不能命令我
-Right, Mr. Hirayama? -Don't start a fight.
-對吧，大叔？ -別吵了
If you don't take over after me, it makes us look bad!
要是你不繼承公司，會丟我們家的臉
-How come you can't understand that? -Ouch! That hurt!
-為什麼你就是不懂呢？ -好痛
Now I'm ticked off!
我生氣了
Damn you!
可惡
Now I'm ticked off again!
氣死我了
Ouch! You jerk! Cut that out!
好痛，你這個混蛋，住手
You give up?
你認輸了？
-You jerk! -Not yet! Damn it!
-你這個混蛋 -還沒，該死
Unbelievable.
真不敢相信
Even dropping tofu wouldn't make such a mess.
就算豆腐摔到地上，也不會這麼亂
Talk about having a fall.
好險沒掉下來
It's not like I expect you to do anything right away.
我不是要你馬上繼承公司
I'm just asking you to make up your mind about the future.
只是要你對未來做好心理準備
That's something that I can't decide yet.
我還沒做出決定
I mean, I'm only 17.
畢竟我才17歲
There are still decades and decades left in my life.
我的人生還有好幾十年
Why do I have to decide right now?
為什麼現在就要決定？
It's just way too cruel.
這樣太殘忍了
This is major.
這下不得了
"Major"? You mean 10,000 yen?
不得了？有一萬日圓？
-100,000 yen. -What?
-是十萬 -什麼？
-They're selling that well? -Yes.
-賣得這麼好？ -對
-These little pieces of scrap?
-那些小廢物？ -沒錯
Students from other schools are coming to buy them too.
其他學校的學生也會來買
Let me have one of these.
送我一個吧
-Sure. Take as many as you like. -All right!
-好，你要幾個都可以 -好耶
But don't you dare forget to advertise.
但要記得幫我打廣告喔
You bet.
當然
All right! Things are going to get even better!
好，一切都很順利呢
Looks like you're enjoying this.
你看起來挺樂在其中的
It does?
是嗎？
You might make a good businessman.
說不定你很適合做生意
No way.
不會吧？
I'm serious.
真的
Totally serious.
我說真的
"Late in the month of February, when the winds blew like a gale,
“2月下旬，狂風大作
and the sky dark as the pit..."
天空漆黑如墨”
A businessman?
生意人？
MEETING ROOM
（會議室）
-Mr. Yokoyama! -Yes?
-橫山老師 -是？
When are you going to get rid of this?
你什麼時候要清掉這個？
Oh, that?
那個啊…
I don't think I can ever get rid of it. Sorry.
這箱我不能丟掉，抱歉
-What? What the heck is in here anyway? -Don't!
-什麼？這裡面到底有什麼？ -不行
No! Don't open it!
不行，別打開
What in the world is this?
這是什麼？
This is the book of poems I published a long time ago, but it never sold.
這是我很久以前出版的詩集 但一直賣不出去
I was going to throw them away,
我本來要丟掉的
but they're memories from my youth, so I couldn't bring myself to.
但這是我年輕時的回憶 所以我捨不得丟
"A used-up pocket warmer will never warm up again."
-“用過的暖暖包不會再變暖了”
No! Please, stop it!
不，拜託，別唸了
Fine! I'll throw them out! I'll throw them all away!
好啦，我丟，我會全部丟掉
DISPOSABLE POCKET WARMERS BY TAKESHI YOKOYAMA
（《拋棄式暖暖包》，橫山武士著）
You don't write this stuff anymore?
你現在不寫這種東西了嗎？
No.
是啊
I haven't written anything at all.
我現在不寫作了
Poems, you know, don't make money.
寫詩賺不了錢
So making a living was more important.
你覺得維持生計更重要？
Yes, I guess you could say that.
是啊，可以這麼說吧
Do you regret it?
你後悔嗎？
No, I don't.
不，我沒有
Not at all?
完全沒有？
You may not believe it, but I really enjoy the job I have now.
雖然你可能不相信 但我真的很喜歡現在的工作
Want to put this in my shop?
這個要不要放在我店裡？
You're kidding.
你開玩笑吧？
Ouch!
好痛
Shuji, how much are our sales?
修二，我們到底賺了多少錢？
Hold on.
等一下
-Hurry up. -Seriously?
-快點 -真的嗎？
No way! Holy cow!
不會吧？天啊
-Show me! -No.
-給我看 -不行
-Don't get too surprised. Okay? Stay calm. -Okay.
-別太驚訝，好嗎？保持冷靜 -好
Voilà!
請看
-Awesome, right? -Awesome!
-很棒吧？ -太棒了
You sure sound excited.
你們還真開心啊
What are you guys talking about?
在聊什麼啊？
Don't worry.
別擔心
I won't be so stupid as to tell you to stop.
我才不會笨到叫你們住手呢
I only came to buy one of those keychains.
我只是來買鑰匙圈的
I'll take one.
我要一個
Sorry, but we're sold out right now.
抱歉，已經賣完了
Then this is to reserve one when you've got more.
那我先預訂吧
Thank you!
謝謝
You kids, do you know which is the front of this coin?
你們知道硬幣的正面是哪一面嗎？
Isn't it obvious?
不是很明顯嗎？
It's this side.
這一面啊
It figures you'd say that.
我就知道你會這麼說
Actually, the cherry-blossom side is the front,
其實櫻花那一面才是正面
but for some reason, now everyone thinks the number side is the front.
但不知道為什麼 現在大家都把數字那面當成正面
The cherry blossoms are the front?
櫻花是正面嗎？
We'd like to think the pretty side is on the front,
我們希望漂亮的一面是正面
but in the real world, things don't always work out that way.
但在現實世界中 事情並不是總能如願
You youngsters obsessed with money!
你們年輕人就是見錢眼開
Don't you dare ever forget that
千萬不能忘記
money has a front side and a back side.
硬幣有正反兩面
Got it?
知道嗎？
Hey.
等等
This one is different than the ones you make, isn't it?
這跟妳做的不一樣，對吧？
Yes.
對
Then it's a fake.
那它就是盜版的
A fake?
盜版的？
I checked it out.
我去調查過了
They are made by students at some other school.
這是其他學校的學生做的
They are clearly a copy of our Nobuta.
這顯然是仿造我們野豬的作品
I never thought there'd be knock-offs.
沒想到會有仿冒品
"It's your fault that I don't sell anymore!"
“都是你害的，害我賣不出去”
That's why our sales have plummeted.
難怪我們的生意一落千丈
What a pain in the neck.
真討厭
I mean, ours is the original.
我們的才是正版啊
Maybe we should just forget it.
或許我們該停手了
It already made everyone happy.
大家已經很開心了
I don't like it!
我不接受
I mean, why are we letting this get the better of us?
我們為什麼要輸給那種東西？
I don't like it either.
我也不接受
I know what to do.
我知道該怎麼做
We'll take all the money we've made and make a better version.
我們拿賺來的錢做更好的版本
Nice. Let's make one better than anyone else's!
好，我們來做比任何人 都還要厲害的作品吧
That's right.
沒錯
I won't let this garbage get the better of us!
我不會被這種垃圾打敗的
"I won't stand for it!"
“我不接受”
I can understand not wanting to give in.
我可以理解你們很不甘心
Right?
對吧？
That's what your father felt when he ran away from home too.
你爸當年也是抱著這種心情 離家出走的
Ran away from home?
離家出走？
My dad did?
我爸嗎？
What? You don't remember that?
什麼？你不記得了嗎？
Not at all.
完全不記得
He couldn't stand to work for his father's company,
他受不了在父親的公司上班
so he took you and his wife, ran away and came to live here.
所以帶著妻小離開 然後搬來我這裡住
HIRAYAMA TOFU SHOP
（平山豆腐店）
Then what happened?
然後呢？
Neither me nor your dad had any money, so the four of us ate nothing but tofu.
因為你爸跟我都沒錢 所以我們四個只能吃豆腐
I don't remember that at all.
我都不記得這些事
Your dad looked all over for work.
你爸到處找工作
But he realized he couldn't support his family,
但他發現自己無法養家活口
so he went back to his dad and asked to work at his company.
所以他回到他爸身邊 要求在他的公司工作
I've…
我…
lost to a lack of money.
還是輸給了錢
He left home because he didn't want to give in,
他當年就是因為不甘心才離開家
but ultimately your dad gave in
但最終你爸還是屈服了
and had to return.
所以還是回家了
That's hot.
好燙
Come on. Over here.
來，來這裡
-Wow.
-天啊
NOBUTA KEYCHAIN NEW VERSION
（新版野豬鑰匙圈）
Let's make one that's better than before.
我們要做出比之前更好的東西
Hurry up! Come on!
快點…
PIG POWERED
（野豬能量，注入）
That was our thought
我們抱持那個想法
when we made this to get revenge on whoever made those fakes.
做了新版鑰匙圈 教訓那些製作仿冒品的人
They're here, amigo.
到貨了，朋友們
Awesome!
太棒了
Our sales goal was 500,000 yen.
我們的目標業績是50萬日圓
I swear we'll achieve it.
我們一定會實現
It's really cute!
真的很可愛喔
It grants your every wish!
能夠實現你所有的願望
You haven't sold any at all.
一個都沒賣出去嘛
It's because you got so cocky, idiots!
還不都是因為你們太囂張，笨蛋
If you feel bad for us, then give us your money!
要是同情我們，就掏錢吧
Business is thriving!
生意興隆啊
What's this? A new version?
這是什麼？新版本？
-That's right. -Wow! This new version sure is cute!
-沒錯 -這個新版的很可愛呢
-The new version! -Wow! It's so cute!
-新版本 -好可愛
-Hey, you got the new version yet? -No.
-妳們有買新版鑰匙圈嗎？ -沒有
This is the new version. What will you wish for this time?
這是新版的，這次要許什麼願好呢？
Shuji, want to go to karaoke today?
修二，今天要不要去唱歌？
Yes! Let's sing to blow off steam!
對啊，一起去唱歌放鬆吧
-Karaoke? -Yes.
-卡拉OK？ -對
-Karaoke? Sure thing! -Really?
-卡拉OK？沒問題 -真的嗎？
-You bet. -Same place?
-當然 -老地方？
-Okay. -Be there!
-好 -一定要來
-Want the new version? No? -You still doing this?
-要買新版的嗎？不要？ -你們還在賣這個？
We sure are.
是啊
-This is the new version. -No thanks. I'm good.
-這是新版的 -不用了，謝謝
-Are you sure? It's new. -It's okay.
-你確定嗎？是新版的 -沒關係
Hang in there.
-加油 -腳踏車
-Wow! This new version is really cute! -New version on sale.
-這個新版的很可愛耶 -新版的在特價
-This must have just come out. -Yes, it just did.
-這是新推出的吧 -沒錯，是新的
-It's the new star. -Wow! It's so cute!
-是最新產品 -好可愛
And there's hardly any! First come, first served!
而且剩不多了，先搶先贏
It's so darn cute! Wow!
這也太可愛了吧
There's still a ton left.
還剩下很多
Let me rub it and make it better!
我幫你揉一揉，就不痛了
And this one is way better than the last one.
這款明明比上一款好多了
Why isn't it selling?
為什麼賣不出去？
Everyone's sick of them.
大家都看膩了吧
But that wouldn't explain all of it.
但那無法解釋一切
This makes no sense.
沒道理
You getting enough calcium?
你有攝取足夠的鈣嗎？
If they're sick of it, then just live with it.
如果他們膩了，我們也沒辦法啊
Right?
對吧？
Shuji!
修二
You okay?
你還好嗎？
Why do you ask?
怎麼了？
I heard the new keychain isn't selling.
聽說新版鑰匙圈賣不出去
Well, it's not that bad.
沒那麼糟啦
-I'll buy one. -No, it's okay.
-我要買一個 -不用，沒關係
-But you need to sell them, right? -Just forget it!
-但你得賣掉它們，對吧？ -我說不用
What?
什麼？
It's okay.
沒關係
PIG POWERED
（野豬能量，注入）
I lost my cool.
我失去理智了
I'm not my normal self.
我不是平常的那個我了
I'm a total freaking jerk.
我現在是個大混蛋
I never should have put so much effort into this.
我不該花這麼多心思在這上面
I seriously should have gone easy on this.
早知道就不要那麼認真了
Then if we failed, I could laugh it off.
如果失敗了，我還能一笑置之
And I never would have acted like I did with Mariko.
我也絕不會對真理子那樣
There's nothing wrong with trying very hard.
努力並沒有錯
But it sucks if it's a failure.
但如果失敗，就很糟糕
But…
但是…
it may have given some people hope.
那或許給了某些人希望
Like people who wished for things.
例如那些許願的人
That doesn't count for anything.
那些不算什麼
Is sales of 100,000 yen or selling 1,000 all that counts?
所以只有賣了十萬日圓 或是一千個才算數？
Yes, it is.
對，沒錯
Stuff like giving people hope
給予人們希望
is just wishful thinking and only helps to ease your conscience.
只是為了減緩自己的良心不安 一廂情願的想法
Everyone!
兩位
We've been screwed again.
我們又被整了
Bang!
砰
Whoever did this is an idiot.
做這件事的人是個白癡
It doesn't matter if paint gets dumped on stuff we couldn't sell anyway.
這些東西都賣不出去 就算潑了油漆也無所謂
I have no idea why anyone wants to do this kind of thing.
我不懂為什麼有人要做這種事
It's probably good this happened.
或許這樣反而是好事
What?
什麼？
We need to move on.
我們必須向前看
Right?
對吧？
I'm home, Mr. Hirayama.
我回來了，大叔
Hey!
喂
What? You're here again?
什麼？你又來啦？
Where's Mr. Hirayama?
大叔呢？
Making deliveries.
送貨啊
I see.
這樣啊
Wait!
等等
I want to talk.
我想跟你談談
About what?
要談什麼？
About taking over after me.
繼承我公司的事
You…
你…
don't have to do it.
不一定要那麼做
What?
什麼？
Why?
為什麼？
Good question.
好問題
Look at this.
你看這個
This is the world that I live in.
這就是我生活的世界
The 10,000-yen bills are all together.
一萬圓鈔票都放在一起
The 100-yen coins are together. The 1-yen coins are together.
一百圓硬幣都放在一起 一圓硬幣都放在一起
They're nicely organized.
全部都整理得很整齊
They're split into their compartments.
它們有各自的格子
The 10,000-yen bills can't fit in with the 100-yen or 1-yen coins.
一萬圓鈔票放不進 一百圓或一圓硬幣的格子
All the 10,000-yen bills are with their kind.
一萬圓鈔票 只能跟一萬圓鈔票放一起
From the outside, it's a pretty dull-looking world.
從外面看，就是個很無聊的世界
You don't have to enter it yet.
你還不用進去那個世界
You keep on being a ten-yen coin sitting on the side of the road.
你就繼續當路邊的十圓硬幣吧
Okay.
好
What is it?
怎麼了？
Come with me!
跟我來
Where?
去哪裡？
Good morning!
早安
Both of you, come with me!
你們兩個都跟我來
School's about to start.
快上課了
That doesn't matter. Come with me!
那不重要，跟我來
What's wrong?
怎麼了？
Dig here.
挖這裡
What?
什麼？
Arf-arf!
汪汪
There's something here.
這裡有東西
I think it's someone's treasure box.
我覺得應該是某人的寶箱
This brings back memories.
好懷念喔
I had one of these as a kid.
我小時候也有這個
Look at this.
看這個
Something that we made
我們做的東西
was a precious treasure to someone.
對某人來說是很珍貴的寶物
It remained special in their hearts.
深深烙印在他們心中
To me, that's enough.
對我來說，這樣就夠了
I'm glad we worked so hard to make them.
有努力去做真是太好了
It's just like Nobuta said.
就像野豬說的
"We need to move on. Right?"
“我們必須向前看，對吧？”
Here. That end has more bean jam.
來，那一半的紅豆餡比較多
What's your treasure, Dad?
爸，你的寶貝是什麼？
That would be you.
就是你啊
When you eat the head of taiyaki…
當你們吃著鯛魚燒的頭
doesn't it make you feel happy?
會不會覺得很幸福？
No.
不會
Right?
對吧？
Yes.
對
I feel normal.
我沒什麼感覺
I see.
好吧
I guess it's just me.
看來只有我會這樣
All right.
太好了
DISPOSABLE POCKET WARMERS BY TAKESHI YOKOYAMA
（《拋棄式暖暖包》）
Mr. Yokoyama's book of poetry was sold at Goyokudo
橫山老師的詩集在豪翼堂販賣
and he enjoyed a brief boom.
他享受了短暫的爆紅
"The white rose is a flower of the rose family."
“白玫瑰是薔薇科的花”
"White Okuda is the son of an ear and nose doctor."
“白奧田是耳鼻喉科醫生的兒子”
-The title is Mirage! -Mirage?
-標題是《海市蜃樓》 -《海市蜃樓》？
Why is that so funny?
有什麼好笑的？
-Was there one that funny in it? -Okuda!
-有這麼好笑嗎？ -奧田
Well, as long as people enjoy it.
好吧，大家喜歡就好
Whoever hasn't handed in the post-graduation survey, hand them in.
還沒交畢業志向調查表的同學 趕快交上來
-Here! -You haven't written it?
-拿去 -你還沒寫？
Bring them forward.
交上來
Like I thought,
跟我想的一樣
I couldn't decide my future
我沒辦法在一週內
in just a week.
決定自己的未來
MEETING ROOM
（會議室）
"Theater."
“劇場”
Yes, she does like theater.
對，她喜歡戲劇
POST-GRADUATION SURVEY
（畢業志向調查表）
"A ten-yen coin on the side of the road. Akira Kusano."
“路邊的十圓硬幣，草野彰”
"Live a happy life. Nobuko Kotani."
“開心過生活，小谷信子”
"Become a proper human.
“成為一個正直的人
Shuji Kiritani."
桐谷修二”
What's with these guys?
這些人是怎麼回事？
I can't tell if they're being facetious…
我看不出來他們是在開玩笑
or serious.
還是認真的
LIVE A HAPPY LIFE. NOBUKO KOTANI
（開心過生活，小谷信子）
A TEN-YEN COIN ON THE SIDE OF THE ROAD. AKIRA KUSANO
（路邊的十元硬幣，草野彰）
BECOME A PROPER HUMAN. SHUJI KIRITANI
（成為一個正直的人，桐谷修二）
While these people work at their jobs,
當這些人工作時
they probably also feel disappointed or happy, or love someone special.
大概也會感到失望、開心 或是愛上某個特別的人
You know what?
我跟你說
I want to quit being a producer.
我不想當改造者了
Is that right?
是嗎？
What? Why?
什麼？為什麼？
It's too painful for me.
對我來說太痛苦了
"Too painful"?
“太痛苦”？
For Nobuta to belong to everyone is painful for me.
要跟大家分享野豬對我來說很痛苦
I want Nobuta to be mine alone.
我希望野豬只屬於我
To be honest, I don't like anyone looking at her.
老實說，我不喜歡有人盯著她看
What's going on inside someone's mind
別人內心的想法
is way beyond anything I can ever imagine.
遠遠超出我的想像
Hold on here.
等一下
Nobuta! I love you!
野豬，我喜歡妳
Today is the last day of the Nobuta production project.
今天是改造野豬計畫的最後一天
Subtitle translation by: Brian Athey
字幕翻譯：黃雅婷